# **Yizhou Shan**

Ph.D. Student School of Electrical and Computer Engineering Purdue University

ys@purdue.edu http://lastweek.io Last Updated: Jul 12, 2019

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests span Distributed System, Operating System, and Computer Architecture, with a focus on building fast and reliable systems for datacenters. I work at Wuklab, Purdue ECE, under the supervision of Prof. Yiying Zhang.

#### **EDUCATION**

Purdue University
Ph.D. in Computer Engineering
(expected)

Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences

Research Assistant

2014-2016

**Beijing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics** 

B.E. in Computer Engineering

2010-2014

#### INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Research Intern, VMware Research

Mentor: Marcos K. Aguilera

Palo Alto, CA, Summer 2019

Research Intern, VMware Research

Mentor: Stanko Novakovic

Palo Alto, CA, Summer 2018

# **PUBLICATIONS**

Stanko Novakovic, **Yizhou Shan**, Aasheesh Kolli, Michael Cui, Yiying Zhang, Haggai Eran, Liran Liss, Michael Wei, Dan Tsafrir, Marcos Aguilera, "Storm: a fast distributed storage system using remote memory primitives", 12th ACM International Systems and Storage Conference (*SYSTOR* '19) (**Best Paper Award**)

**Yizhou Shan,** Yutong Huang, Yilun Chen, Yiying Zhang, "LegoOS: A Disseminated, Distributed OS for Hardware Resource Disaggregation", 13th USENIX Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation (*OSDI '18*) (**Best Paper Award**)

**Yizhou Shan**, Shin-Yeh Tsai, Yiying Zhang, "Distributed Shared Persistent Memory", Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing 2017 (*SoCC '17*)

#### WORKSHOPS AND POSTERS

**Yizhou Shan**, Yutong Huang, Yiying Zhang, "Challenges in Building and Deploying Disaggregated Persistent Memory", 10th Annual Non-Volatile Memories Workshop (*NVMW* '19)

**Yizhou Shan**, Shin-Yeh Tsai, Yiying Zhang, "Distributed Shared Persistent Memory", 9th Annual Non-Volatile Memories Workshop (*NVMW '18*)

**Yizhou Shan**, Yiying Zhang, "Disaggregating Memory with Software-Managed Virtual Cache", the 2018 Workshop on Warehouse-scale Memory Systems (*WAMS* '18) (co-located with ASPLOS '18)

Yiying Zhang, **Yizhou Shan**, Sumukh Hallymysore, "Disaggregated Operating System", 17th International Workshop on High Performance Transaction Systems (*HPTS '17*)

**Yizhou Shan**, Yilun Chen, Yutong Huang, Sumukh Hallymysore, Yiying Zhang, "Lego: A Distributed, Decomposed OS for Resource Disaggregation", Poster at the 26th ACM Symposium on Operating Systems Principles (*SOSP '17*)

**Yizhou Shan**, Sumukh Hallymysore, Yutong Huang, Yilun Chen, Yiying Zhang, "Disaggregated Operating System", Poster at the ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing 2017 (*SoCC '17*)

#### **AWARDS**

SYSTOR'19 Best Paper Award OSDI '18 Jay Lepreau Best Paper Award OSDI '18 Student Travel Grant SOSP '17 Student Travel Grant SoCC '17 Student Travel Grant

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## **Optimize Page Fault Handling (Work-In-Progress)**

2019-

VMware Research

Ancient old page fault handling is the driving wheel for many emerging datacenter systems and applications. But the page fault handling mechanism was designed for millisecond-level disk operations, there is a performance mismatch when it is used by fast devices like RDMA, or PM. We are now trying to close the gap.

# Disaggregated FPGA Platform (Work-In-Progress)

2018-

Purdue University

We are building a generalized FPGA platform for future disaggregated datacenters. We envision the FPGA will be attached to ToR directly and will give services to remote monolithic servers. We are now building OS services in the FPGA and deploy couple emerging applications into it.

# **Disaggregated Operating System**

2017-2018

Purdue University

We propose a new OS model called the splitkernel to manage disaggregated systems. Splitkernel disseminates traditional OS functionalities into loosely-coupled monitors, each of which runs on and manages a hardware component. Using the splitkernel model, we built LegoOS, a new OS designed for hardware resource disaggregation.

# **Distributed Shared Persistent Memory**

2016-2017

Purdue University

We propose Distributed Shared Persistent Memory (DSPM), a new framework for using persistent memories in datacenter environments. We designed and implemented *Hotpot*, the first DSPM system in Linux kernel. Hotpot provides low-latency, transparent memory accesses, data persistence, data reliability and high availability.

# Non-Volatile Memory (NVM) Emulator

2015-2016

Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences

We designed and implemented a NVM emulator in Linux kernel, which leverages Intel's Performance Monitoring Unit to emulate NVM's slower read/write latency and smaller bandwidth on physical DRAM. This emulator runs on baremetal x86 machines.

ARMv8 CPU Project 2013

Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences

I participated in the Register-Transfer Level design and verification of some blocks within cache unit and load-store unit. It is commercial project collaborated with Huawei.